H I want to ask you for advice on how to
lead a secular Buddhist group. People
are coming to our group expecting
meditation to relax them. Uh we don't
read sutas or think about them. New
people who are coming most probably are
not keeping with.
>> So what should we do so that people can
benefit from correct Buddhist practice?
>> Well, you just answered it yourself.
Read the sutas and teach them to keep
the precepts. Otherwise, you might as
well not call it the terraada Buddhist
group. >> Yeah, I agree.
>> Yeah, I agree.
But there is an big conviction that
people don't want to read sutas because
it's boring to for them.
>> Yeah. Then then basically they would go
to another group.
But if they come to to uh
learn about the Buddhist teaching, you
present them the Buddhist teaching. If
they don't like it, that's not your
problem. It's not like your goal is not to try
It's not like your goal is not to try
and keep as many people as possible
interested. Your goal is to show to
those that want to follow it what to
follow. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
Um yeah. And uh what what to do with
this expectation
that meditation is some kind of
relaxation technique?
>> Well, as I said like people everybody
that starts they don't really they can't
tell the difference. So everybody will
have their own expectations as puggenas
that they come from. So what you do is
you you provide them the right
information and then if they if they
don't like it they can find something
else that suits their preferences more.
But you'll be surprised how despite of
how wrong their expectation might be. If
people were to hear the right thing many
of them would recognize that they want
to do it.
So they come with an expectation but you
provide them with the actual teachings.
So the sutras
uh the precepts the training in those
things that we often talk about and
those that see the value in that they
will stay those that don't will find
something else that would cater to their
needs. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I have a theory that everyone deep
inside know what is the truth but we
just choose to not see it.
>> Well exactly you can't make them do it.
So if they don't want to if if if if
they don't want to practice the Buddhist
teaching once they find out what it is,
that's up to them and that's fine.
But the worst is to actually
misrepresent the Buddhist teaching
because you think people might not like
it. Yeah, it's always somebody's not
going to like something. But if you want
to run a group, your duty is to present
it as clearly as possible what the
Buddha was teaching, what the
requirements are,
even if that puts everybody away.
>> Would you recommend some sutas for
starters? >> Well, I think just you could just go
>> Well, I think just you could just go
generally just go through Majimanikaya
sutas. Um,
Um,
they kind of a certain like balance, you
know, they're not too short, they're not
too long. and they always obviously
revolve around the important points. So
just just any pretty much engagement
with the with the sutras can sort of uh
point people in the right direction. So
at least they'll know okay you know I
can do this on my own as well. I can
read this, I can study this uh I can try
and understand uh what these texts kind
of require from you to do
um if you're interested in following the
Buddhist teaching. Yeah.
>> Should we advise them to do some
contemplation like for example ask
yourself are you suffering? Why are you
suffering? >> Yeah. Yeah. All of that of course. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. All of that of course. Yeah.
Like kind of um a certain like a guided
type of qu questioning reflections and
so on. Um but uh as I said
your job is to present them with what
the Buddha was teaching. So you might
see that oh half of these people here
come because they think the Buddha is
teaching something completely different.
So therefore I won't tell them what the
Buddha is. No you tell them and if that
makes them leave they leave. New people
will come.
Yeah. And I guess we are not going to
just remove the meditation because it's
it's used use it so it is used. often and
used use it so it is used. often and
people expect expectations.
>> Yeah, you don't have to remove the
period of sitting quietly
>> but you certainly remove the wrong
instructions of meditation.
>> Mhm.
>> That are simply not found in the sutras
and come with the commentaries and
contemporary kind of terra watering down
and perversion of the teaching. So just
yeah go through a suta do some
questioning some basic kind of
reflection on certain themes that are
from the sutras encourage people to
think about it and then tell them sit
quietly now with those reflections
so let's assume I am new person who
comes to your particular Buddhist group
I I have expectation that I want to just
relax to feel better I came here to to
relax >> well you tell them you came to wrong
>> well you tell them you came to wrong
place this is another relaxation center.
Go to a spa center if you want to relax.
In this place, we learn what the Buddha
was teaching, which is suffering and
freedom from it,
>> which is not going to be a relaxing
truth for most people when they first
hear it.
>> Okay?
>> So, you have no duty or obligation to
cater >> to the expectations of people when they
>> to the expectations of people when they
come for the Buddhist teaching.
>> Mhm.
>> Supposedly, at least.
>> Okay. So, you told me this. I decided
still not to leave. So what's next? I am
I want to relax because I am suffering.
>> Yeah. So the only way to truly relax
from your suffering is to understand it.
So you have to start study the sutas,
training the precepts
until you relax on the right level.
Yeah. If you want a quick fix, you came
to a wrong place.
>> Okay. And often I got question, we got
question when some new people come is
Buddhism a religion.
>> Uh it depends how you look at it I
suppose. Um I mean it certainly today is
a religion because when you look at the
Buddhism as as um the way it was spread
through through various Asian countries,
it is their religion. It's their it's on
the level of their belief on the level
of their superstition. Just like how
Christianity is in in Europe for most
people. But the practicing aspect of
Buddhism or the pract practicing aspect
of any religion, it's not really
religion. Religion is basically when it becomes
Religion is basically when it becomes
kind of a part of identity and belief of
people they don't really practice. They
don't want to practice. They're
satisfied with that external just as I
said identifier.
So in terms of its customs, rules,
rituals and stuff, yeah, of course it's
very religious like everything else that
has reached that level of institution.
But is the dharma a religion? No, of
course not. It's not even a philosophy
for that matter. It's it's a it's a
specific um
recipe for a certain type of behavior,
certain types of reflections that can
bring certain type of understanding.
That's it. So it's very specific.
>> When people ask like how long will it
take me to make some progress? This is
the progress in Dhama. What should I
answer? >> Well, it depends how long do they make a
>> Well, it depends how long do they make a
good quality effort.
In the same somebody goes to become a
carpenter, hasn't even started yet, but
wants to know how long it will take me
to become a master expert. Well, it's up
to you. If you do it rightly from the
start, it will take you very little
time. If not, so if if if that's what's
important to that person, how long will
it take me to reach that? Well, then it
should be equally important to them to
start doing it rightly from the
beginning and not delay the work. Um
Um
yeah. And uh what should I tell people?
Like we are advising people to watch
your videos but some people are saying
>> um like you are too harsh in speech like
you are not positive enough
>> like you don't have this image of smiley
monk. >> So and and they are it is too much for
>> So and and they are it is too much for
them. Well, it might be too much.
you have to work your way up to be able
to understand the Buddhist teaching
in the same sense like those you know
there those instances in the sutras when
that man went to the Buddha and said his
son died or something and he said um he
was saying how children are the greatest
happiness and the greatest wealth and
the greatest benefit and the Buddha said
no children are the the greatest
suffering the source of the biggest
suffering and he disagreed He dismissed
he he said something and then went to
these random gamblers and drunkards
to ask them the same question because he
knew they will agree with him.
So if people are not willing to question
their own preferences of what the
practice is while at the same time
knowing that they don't know what the
practice is but still use their own
preferences as a criteria of oh I like
this I don't like that then there is no
dhammer for them like they they're not
able to even begin thinking rightly.
So if somebody expects the dharma to be
a smiley laughing monk just talking
about happiness and positive thoughts, I
mean there's nothing wrong to expect
that. But then if you meet somebody that
tells you the opposite, do you just
dismiss it on account of a mere
preference because he doesn't look right
or doesn't play the right part that I
expect him to play? Or do you question
your own preferences and beliefs?
Because what position are you in? Are
you the one seeking the way out of
suffering? In which case, if you
genuinely think your head is on fire,
you would certainly be considering all
options that are presented to you. You
wouldn't be dismissing them because you
have you think you have a privilege to
do so. Oh, I don't like this. I don't
need to listen to it.
So, in other words, they're not serious
enough to practice to begin with because
if they were, they would think about
things in both ways regardless of their
preferences.
So if they want a if they want a happy
monk and positive thoughts, they don't
want the dharma really. They just want a
uh an engaging even intoxicating
spiritual dimension to their very kind
of household worldly life that they
refuse. They don't really want to
change. >> Is there a place for such people who
>> Is there a place for such people who
really don't want dharma but they want
just kind of Buddhist practice for lay
people? >> Say again. Is there what
>> Say again. Is there what
>> a place for such people?
>> What do you mean?
>> In our group, for example,
when >> Well, it depends how what what do you
>> Well, it depends how what what do you
want your group to be about? Do you want
your group to be about something that
just caters to your average Buddhist
with whatever preconceived notions of
Buddhism they bring in? Do you want to
just cater to that or do you want your
group to be uh about the actual Buddhist
teaching? In which case there is no
place for those that don't want to
follow the actual Buddhist teaching.
>> But maybe they just want this teachings
for lay people from Buddha.
>> It's the same teaching.
>> He didn't teach a different dharma to
lay people. And when he was teaching lay
people how to look after their wives and
be generous and good householder, that
was not the dharma. That was just be a
good person so you have a good rebirth.
And he would teach them that because he
knew they won't understand the dharma.
>> So your definition of dharma is things
that uproots the suffering.
>> Of course, that's the only definition
there is.
>> Mhm. Because many people have definition
like all teachings are dharma.
Everything in the world is da.
>> Yeah. Because they haven't read the
sutas and haven't read the actual
dharma. They just been hearing
secondhand perverted accounts and
develop their own notions of who knows
what. basically some generic religious
spirituality advita and so on. Um so as
the Buddha said repeatedly dhamma only
has one taste
which is freedom from suffering in the
same sense the ocean has only one taste
of salt.
Um so whether he was teaching it to
householders or or or monks if it was
the dhamma being taught the principles
the gradual the virtue the restraint the
taming of the mind uh reflections on the
certain certain topics that was no
exception it was the same and they were
as soon as they say that whether
householder or a monk this is the this
is the path
yeah so if people come there and they
don't want to do that then there is no
place in that group for them not because
you refuse to let them in. It's because
they refuse to follow what's required.
It's again like you go to a carpentry
school and you say, "But I don't want to
work with the wood.
I don't like that. But I want to be a
carpenter. I still want to be a
carpenter, but I don't want to work with
wood." Does that make any sense? No. By
any measure of of rational thought,
that's insane. Especially when you find
out what carpentry entails. If you still
if you still want to insist on your own
preferences,
>> should we also include some kind of
practice of generosity?
>> Sure. Yeah.
>> Any advice what it might be? Well, I
don't really know, but you could
probably find out, you know, places, uh,
communities, things like that that are
in need of help that can be contributed
towards and just organize things like
that. Yeah.
Like go and volunteer somewhere as a
group basically.
>> Yeah. Absolutely.
>> Okay. Okay. So many teachers
you are focusing on five precepts but
many teachers
put emphasis on eightfold path and other
parts of path as well.
>> Mhm.
>> Um so
>> well those teachers should read the
sutas because uh they very clearly say
that there is no eightful path without
the right view.
So if you think you're practicing
eightful path without being a sapana,
you're not. As simple as that. Right
view comes first. All the individual
factors of the eightful path arise from
the right view. I mean the suta cannot
be any more clear on that. So I would I
would advise them to basically read the
sutas. >> How about mundan
>> How about mundan
view?
>> What about it? Because there is a split
for mundane right view and
>> well in a mundane right view again there
is noble path in it. The mundane right
view is just the recognition
pretty much recognizing the weight of
your actions
that you are inseparable from them. um
that there are things that basically um
your views will not necessarily
comprehend there and then
but that's why you also recognize the
possibility of existence of such things
so you don't dismiss them.
So in other words the mundane right view
is just puta who is kind of more acutely
and more transparently more
authentically aware of his own
situation. So it's described like there
is mother, there is father, there is
good action, there is bad action, there
are results of action because even those
basic things today if you were to press
people to ask them for it, they would
kind of fall into these views of denial
or a cover up and so on and everything
would just be boiled down to certain I
don't know like reductionist psychology
or or biology or physiology and in
reality nothing's real. Everything is
constantly changing. All of those are
just forms of denial. So even most
Buddhists today that follow this
commentarial level of teaching don't
even have the mundane right view of
recognizing no there is good action and
bad action. There is good thought and
bad thought and the weight of those
things are on me for myself. There is no
shared world here that we all partake
together. It's me and everybody else.
That's how things work. So I am the one
bound with my own actions heir to them
and going to inherit everything implicit
to the extent that I cannot even fathom.
Not just yeah I can measure the action
and the reaction that comes with it. No
the implications of your actions can
span over course of who knows how many
lifetimes and you can't even fed them
that at a time yet they will keep the
the results will be keep coming back.
So the fact that there are those things
that you cannot even comprehend does not
give you the uh rational basis to
dismiss them. You know like usually like
people say oh what's the proof that
there is rebirth? Well what's the proof
that there isn't one.
So you have no proof for either yet the
lack of proof for rebirth immediately
justifies vast majority of people in
their belief that there is no rebirth
because there's no proof for it. It's
like but there is no proof against it
either. So why did you take up that
belief? And you would see oh because you
were not transparent and clear enough
that you are in a position of not
knowing either. And therefore falling
into a belief about one or the other
will basically just be a way of a
compromise and a cover up.
Let's say that some new people are
coming and uh should we tell them that
where is a river and then then should
contemplate that they have kama and those come this
that they have kama and those come this
kama will be
brought to the next rebirth. Well yes
again like uh in a in a broad strokes
but they will not necessarily
um develop the mundane right view either
for them like it needs to come
internally a person themselves
internally need to see that oh I'm in a position of
need to see that oh I'm in a position of
not knowing this for sure
therefore whatever I choose to believe
will in return reflect on my course of
action that's why when they asked the
Buddha the same question he said
basically to to recognize that well I
don't know which one's true but usually
if I'm dismissing the rebirth if I'm
dismissing the implications of future
kind of results of my action I won't pay
much attention to what I do in this life
I will be careless I will be acting out
of greed aversion delusion if I kind of
lean on the side poof there could be a
rebirth which means then there will be
implications and results of my actions
to the a lot greater degree than I can
measure in this life then you would pay
attention to what you do what you say
what you do to others and how you behave
but it needs to come from your own as I
said internal recognition and set of
values not just I'm a Buddhist I believe
in rebirth
it's like well that did not make you any
more transparent
than before you just took another
external stance in regard to your
position because you refuse to endure
that ambiguity of your situation
let's say that some new people are
coming and they are not keeping
precepts. Should we advise them doing
contemplation of anata, sickness, death?
>> I mean like in broad strokes you could
point out that those are the
contemplations that one needs to
develop. But then you also need to very
specifically tell them that
contemplating such things without a
basis of virtue and certain degree of
being able to contain your own mind will
not end well
has a risk carries a risk of not ending
well because you are proddding you're
because you are proddding you're
provoking your mind now towards the
contexts and contemplations that
naturally no mind wants to think but at
the same time you're keeping it wild to
do whatever he wants.
So you agitate it and then you make it
and then you allow it to behave
whichever way it wants as a result of
that agitation. Well, it's not going to
be good.
>> Is it safe?
Is it any safe contemplation for people
who are not keeping?
>> Uh the the value of keeping the precepts
and the danger of not keeping them.
That's a safe contemplation for them.
>> Yeah, makes sense.
So we can just talk about why keeping it
habits and is good for you.
and is good for you.
>> Yeah. And why not keeping them is
dangerous. Again, not because somebody will say,
Again, not because somebody will say,
"Oh, you're not a good Buddhist." But
because it keeps the very core of your
being untamed, wild, whimsical, u
subject to to to to like extreme
fluctuations of moods and exposures on the emotional
of moods and exposures on the emotional
level, and you're going to suffer as a
result of it.